One more topic to cover before we go into our exercise is inheritance.
As we saw, these classes in Python help us make reusable code.
And I'm going to make a new file here.
I'm going to save it and I'm going to call it vehicle.py.
Okay.
Sometimes we want our classes to share properties between each other.
So we saw that my car had four wheels.
Well, I could also have a motorcycle.
And my motorcycle will have two wheels, but it still runs.
So inheritance is a way to kind of make types that have shared attributes.
And it helps us break up an organizer code in a hierarchy from more generic to more specific.
Objects that belong to classes higher up the hierarchy, the more generic ones.
They're accessible via the more specific subclasses, but not vice versa.
Earlier, we saw that the bull type is so close.
Sorry, I forgot about arguments and instead of scrolling through my history, I'm just going to show you, you know, the quickest way to get help on that.
So the first thing is the class and the second thing is the class or two bull.
So subclass X.
So I would ask is subclass of bull and int both of the arguments have to be a class there.
Okay, true.
So just like we saw earlier, this bullion, the bullion subclass.
It took all of the properties of int and then it added to and extended them.
Right, so it's still got all the stuff that instewonder the hood.
You're going to be weird and add them together, but it has a lot more properties.
We can do the same thing with our classes as well.
So looking at this vehicle.py file, I'm going to make a class vehicle.
And I'm going to make a dunder in it for it.
What does the first argument to dunder in it have to be?
And I'm going to put a make here and a model and the type of fuel that it takes.
Just like in other types of functions, I can pass in a default argument here.
Just remember that all of those default arguments have to come last in order.
How do I save these parameters that are passed into my instance?
Right, so self dot make is going to be the passed in make.
Self dot model is going to be the passed in model.
And self dot fuel is going to be the passed in fuel.
For you more advanced folks who want to do more research after class,
there's a great thing in Python 37 called a data class that is kind of a special type of more advanced class that kind of helps you do a lot less of this kind of template stuff.
Because the more arguments you add if you want to save them to the instance,
you have to kind of have a long list of assignments here.
Okay, and then I'm going to make a new class now for my car.
And it's going to inherit and extend from vehicle.
And in order to do that, I add some parentheses here.
And then I put in the class that I want to extend from.
So notice this is the type, it's not an instance, right?
This is the type I want to inherit from.
And my car is going to have its own constructor.
And it's going to take self again.
It's going to take them make the model.
It's going to take the fuel.
But it's also going to take another optional argument.
Number of wheels.
If I want to.
Call the constructor on my vehicle.
Because I already do, you know, I wrote the code to be most of the stuff.
Just added on a little bit of extra.
I have to use a special keyword in Python called super.
And if you use Python 2 or if you've seen Python 2,
this super keyword is just a bit of a mess.
In Python 3, it's a lot easier.
You just use the super keyword.
You pass, you kind of call it with this empty.
You're storing it and you do the method of the super class that you want to call.
And then you pass in the arguments.
So this just calls this with all of the parameters I gave.
But we missed something.
We're passing in a new parameter.
We have to do with number of wheels.
Assign it to self, right?
Hey, I'm going to copy over this reload stuff.
This reload comment to the top here.
Sorry, it's a little bit annoying.
We're not usually changing the file this much.
And I'm going to open my Rappel again.
So now I'm going to say import vehicle.
And I'm going to make a new car.
I'm going to say my super equals.
Actually, before I do that, I'm going to make a new vehicle, right?
This super class.
Maybe I have a 4 by 4, right?
It doesn't really fit into the other categories.
So I'm going to say that my 4 by 4 is a vehicle.
And the make of it is, I don't know anything about 4 by 4s.
So I'm going to say the make of it is zoom.
And the model is it goes fast.
And the fuel is cooking oil.
Very efficient.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I had to do a vehicle dot vehicle.
Usually we just say from vehicle import the vehicle class.
But because I have to reload, we're kind of doing it this way.
Okay.
So now my 4 by 4, it has a make.
It has a model.
And it has a fuel.
I'm going to make a new instance of car.
So I'm going to say my Subaru is a vehicle dot cars.
And the make is Subaru.
And the model is cross track.
And the fuel is diesel.
I'm sorry I called it car.
So vehicle dot car.
Okay.
So I have my Subaru instance now.
My Subaru has a make.
My Subaru has a model.
My Subaru has fuel.
Does my Subaru have the number of wheels variable?
Does it?
It's always default.
That's right.
Does see what did I name it here?
My 4 by 4.
Does my 4 by 4 have a number of wheels?
Does it?
No.
Right?
Vehicle object has no attribute number of wheels.
My car does my vehicle doesn't.
And this is a good opportunity for me now.
If I wanted to make a motorcycle,
you can make a new class that has the default number of wheels to be two.
And that really kind of cuts down on data duplication.
Makes this code a lot more.
Composable a lot more easier to maintain.
Right?
If I had a method on vehicle.
Let's say, you know.
Is my fuel efficient?
Is eco friendly?
And I would take in self.
And if the fuel is equal to gas,
we're going to return false.
Otherwise, we're going to ever turn true.
My self.fuel, of course.
And I know that this self.fuel is always on my vehicle.
Even if I removed this, it wouldn't matter because the fuel here is by default gas.
So now I'm going to go in.
I'm going to reload this.
And then I'm going to say, you know,
I'm going to go back to my 4 by 4.
And make a new instance.
I'm going to make a new instance of my Subaru.
Subaru, cross track.
Does my 4 by 4?
Can I call this?
Is eco friendly?
Method on it?
Can I call it on my Subaru?
No, because you didn't bring it in in Subaru.
I didn't.
But what did I do here by calling a super dye net?
I made a called a net on my vehicle.
And my car inherits from vehicle.
So any methods available to my vehicle will also be available on my car.
That's how we encourage car code reuse.
If I made a new motorcycle class that inherited from vehicle,
it would also have this eco friendly method.
So instead of making motorcycle and car and a 4 by 4,
that all have their own version of this method,
we cut down on code duplication and put it in one place.
The last topic here, I'm not going to talk about very much.
I just want to give you a heads up.
Unlike in other languages, in Python, you can have multiple inheritance.
So you can inherit from multiple different other classes at once.
And things get a bit hairy, but one use case of this is something called a mixing.
So a mixing might be a class that just has a method like this on it.
And I don't care if my 4 by 4 is eco friendly.
I'm driving it through the grass and mowing it down.
And what do I care if it's, you know, gas or solar?
So where I, in the cases where I do care maybe like a car,
I can have an additional class that I inherit from that just has this method.
So one of my favorite, one common use case for this,
you might see if you're declaring database tables in Python.
You might have some mix-ins for something like a date column,
where you don't necessarily want, you want to have a date,
a created on date on all of your objects, just, you know, for compliance reasons.
But you don't want to have to say, you know, class vehicle dot date equals whatever,
class motor cycle dot date equals whatever.
So you can just have a mix-in class that will create that column for you.
And provide all of the methods that you might need to use it.
I've seen Python code that on an objects that don't,
or classes that don't inherit from anything else,
but the object keyword is the object that they inherit from,
instead of just saying the name of the class column,
they'll have object after the class definition.
So that is, yeah, that is one of the differences between Python 2 and Python 3.
In Python 3, you don't need to do that anymore.
It's redundant, you know,
simple as better than complex.
You can still do it, and it's not a syntax error.
You just shouldn't.